<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation inhibiting the importation of vvhale finnes into his Maiesties dominions by any, but the Muscouy Company.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 1851.b.3[6]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99891125</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99891125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">188356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C10:2[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation inhibiting the importation of vvhale finnes into his Maiesties dominions by any, but the Muscouy Company.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets (versos blank).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, printers to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno M. DC. XIX. [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: ... Greenwich, the eighteenth day of May, in the seuenteenth yeere of our raigne ..</note>
                  <note>Arms 11; Steele notation: Wansted,  bid  2) vpon  the.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Muscovy Company --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Exclusive licenses --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Whalebone --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:188356:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</head>
               </figure>¶ By the King. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation inhibiting the Importation of Whale Finnes into his Maieſties Dominions by any, but the Muſcouy Company.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Wee by Our Proclamation giuen at Wanſted,</hi> the eleuenth day of September in the twelfth yeere of Our reigne of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons therein expreſſed, and for the incouragement of Our wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Subiects, the company of Merchants trading for Muſcouia, Greeneland and the parts adioyning, commonly called the Muſcouia Company, did ſtraitly and expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid and prohibit all Aliens and Strangers whatſoeuer, and alſo all Our owne Subiects (others then the ſayd Muſcouia Merchants, and that in their ioynt ſtock) to bring into any Our Kingdomes, and Dominions any Whale Finnes vpon paine of confiſcation of the ſame, and of Our high indignation and diſpleaſure, and of ſuch further puniſhment as ſhould be meet to be inflicted vpon the Offenders for their contempt in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as We are giuen to vnderſtand, That Our ſayd Proclamation took not that good effect, nor found that due obedience and conformity which We expected: We haue therefore in further manifeſtation of our former intentions and gracious fauor towards the ſayd Company, thought good eftſoones to publiſh Our Royall pleaſure heerein, and to reuiue and quicken Our ſayd former Proclamation, which We cannot but take in ill part, hath beene ſo much neglected: And therefore We doe by theſe preſents ſtraitly charge, prohibit, and forbid, aſwell all Alliens and Strangers whatſoeuer, as alſo Our naturall born Subiects and Denizens, That they nor any of them (other then the ſayd Muſcouia Merchants, and that in their ioynt ſtocke onely) ſhall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth directly or indirectly import, or bring into Our Kingdomes and Dominions, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, any Whale Finnes, vpon paine of forfeiture, and confiſcation of the ſame, whether they be found on board of any Ship, Hoy, Boate, or Bottome, or layd on land
<pb facs="tcp:188356:2"/> in any warehouſe, ſtorehouſe, ſhop, cellar, or any other place whatſoeuer, and vpon paine of Our high Indignation and diſpleaſure, and ſuch other puniſhment, as by Our Court of Starre chamber ſhalbe thought meet to be inflicted vpon them, or any of them, as contemners of Our Royall will and commandement in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>And Wee doe likewiſe ſtraitly charge, prohibite and forbid, aſwell all Aliens and Strangers, as Our naturall borne Subiects &amp; Denizens (other then the ſayd Muſcouia Merchants) that they nor any of them doe preſume to buie, vtter, ſell, barter or contract for, any Whale finnes, knowing the ſame to be imported into any of our Realmes or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions contrary to Our wil &amp; pleaſure heerein declared, vpon paine of Our high indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and diſpleaſure, &amp; ſuch further puniſhment as by Our ſaid Court of Starre cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall bee thought meet to be inflicted vpon ſuch offenders, as contemners alſo of Our Royall commandement. And to the end this Our pleaſure may take the better effect, We doe heereby charge, and command all Cuſtomers, Comptrollers, Searchers, Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Farmors, and Collectors of Our Cuſtomes, and other our Officers and Miniſters, carefully to attend euery one in his ſeuerall place, the execution heereof, and in no wiſe to permit or ſuffer any Whale finnes directly or indirectly, openly or priuately to be brought, or imported into any Our Kingdomes or Dominions, contrary to Our Royal pleaſure heerein expreſſed, or being ſo imported, that they doe not permit, or ſuffer the ſame to bee colourably cuſtomed for other goods and Merchandize, but that foorthwith they or ſome of them doe ſeize and take to Our vſe all ſuch Whalefinnes as ſhall be ſo imported, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately vpon ſuch ſeizure made, to giue notice thereof in writing to Our Regiſter for forfeitures in Our Cuſtome houſe in the Port of London, vpon paine to vndergoe ſuch puniſhment, as ſhalbe thought meet by the Lords of Our Priuie Councell.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe Our intent and meaning is, That the ſayd Muſcouie Company, and none other, ſhall or may buy, and ſell, barter, or contract for, any ſuch Whalefinnes, as being imported contrary to this Our Proclamation ſhalbe confiſcate and ſeized, and the ſame, being ſold by the ſayd Company, may be afterward bought, contracted for, and vſed by any other Our Subiects at their wil and pleaſure. Any thing heerein contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at Our Mannour of Greenwich,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the eighteenth day of May, in the ſeuenteenth yeere of our Raigne of England, France, and Ireland, and of Scotland the two and fiftieth.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, Printers to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie. <hi>Anno. M.DC.XIX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
